Frances Ward Harrington Newspaper Collection
Frances Ward Harrington Newspaper Collection
1783-1940
Harrington, Frances Ward.
11 items.
18th and 19th century newspapers from in and around New York State.
149212
Biographical History
Frances Ward Harrington (1904?-1990) was an American magazine editor. Born in Wichita, Kansas, she graduated from Syracuse University in 1924. Among other career highlights she was editor of Mademoiselle and editor in chief of Charm magazine.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Frances Ward Harrington Newspaper Collection consists of several 18th and 19th century newspapers from in and around New York State. Local newspapers include issues of the Syracuse Daily Star (29 Jul 1846), the Hudson Gazette (8 Feb 1825), the Albany Gazette (11 Nov 1796) and the Western Herald and Steubenville Gazette (17 Oct 1838). There is also a page from Ballou's Pictorial Drawing Room Companion (1856) with illustrations and text about Syracuse.
Of particular interest are the earliest and the most recent items in the collection. The earliest item is an issue of the Pennsylvania Gazette from 16 Jul 1783, which contains the text of a letter from George Washington addressed to the Governors of all the states and written on the occasion of the disbanding of the army. In it he lays out four principles which he believes are "essential to the well-being, I may even say, to the existence of the United States." The fourth item is "that pacific and friendly disposition among the people...which will induce them forget their local prejudices and policies; to make those mutual concessions, which are requisite to the general prosperity; and, in some instances, to sacrifice their individual advantages to the interest of the community."
The most recent item is the 18 Jun 1940 issue of PM, with the large headline, "Hitler Joins Mussolini in Munich" and the sub-headline, "Dictators confer today on price they propose to exact for stopping destruction of France...Unconditional surrender reported only basis for negotiations..."
Arrangement of the Collection
No particular order.
Separated Material
The collection originally also included a number of autograph letters and documents from notable individuals, including Mary Queen of Scots, and assorted other items. At the time of processing some could no longer be located. The others have been separate into individual small collections. For a full list, see the finding aids files.
Subject and Genre Headings
New York State; Harrington, Frances Ward -- collector.; Washington, George, 1732-1799.; Frank Leslie's illustrated newspaper.; Pennsylvania gazette (Philadelphia, Pa.); Syracuse daily star.; Newspapers -- 18th century.; Newspapers -- 19th century.; Newspapers -- New york (State); World War, 1939-1945 -- Newspapers.; Syracuse (N.Y.) -- Newspapers.; Newspapers.; Clippings (information artifacts)
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Francis Ward Harrington.
Inventory
- Newspapers
  - Spencer Phips, 31 May 1756; Lt. Gov. of Massachusetts; text of speech, printed in newspaper (Package 1)
  - Pennsylvania Gazette, Philadelphia, 16 Jul 1783; contains text of George Washington's letter dated 12 Jun 1783, on disbanding of army (Package 1)
  - Albany Gazette, 11 Nov 1796 (Package 1)
  - Hudson Gazette, 8 Feb 1825 (Package 1)
  - The Evening Post (NYC), 20 Feb 1834 (Package 1)
  - Western Herald and Steubenville Gazette, 17 Oct 1838 (Package 1)
  - Syracuse Daily star, 29 Jul 1846; complete issue (Package 1)
  - Ballou's Pictorial Drawing Room Companion, 1856; 2 pages, pictures and text about Syracuse (Package 1)
  - New York Herald, 3 Apr 1862 (Package 1)
  - Frank Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper, 8 Apr 1876; 1 page (Package 1)
  - PM, 18 Jun 1940; headline: "Hitler Joins Mussolini in Munich" (Package 1)